topic: Tools
deck: CS::Tools
uid_tag: tools
notes:
        -
                uuid: 0a283dbf-a7ba-40e4-9811-7a1dd7701a89
                front: GUI hex editor
                back: "`bless`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: df69d00c-8158-481f-9cd2-6a149a2a2659
                topic: Valgrind
                front: Attach debugger on first error
                back: "`valgrind --db-attach=yes` ..."
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 6ad7a641-f416-49c1-8f8b-3cb6860ae469
                topic: Valgrind
                front: Save log of errors
                back: "`valgrind --log-file=xyzzy.log` ..."
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 6e27637f-16e3-4200-8c4b-e3b1c8018ddb
                front: Output file with line numbers
                back: "`nl`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 67afaaa3-a061-4ece-9368-ec0f909d5f4f
                front: "List directory, showing file types"
                back: "`ls -F`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: e92c02d9-92f0-4643-bad2-1682c951c555
                front: "PIC microchip simulator"
                back: "`gpsim`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 5ba25172-5bbb-4a50-becf-6c249c7d6019
                front: "PIC microchip utilities"
                back: "`gputils`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 7b375c52-b014-41a1-8091-9c2c7b29b9ab
                front: "YouTube downloader"
                back: "`youtube-dl`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 3860f642-a093-4772-8b4d-980b2fd2f28c
                front: "Disk usage visualizer"
                back: "`baobab`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 1a5e809c-5ff6-46eb-ab6a-82a0d8bfacd8
                front: "Paint program"
                back: "`mypaint`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 153080ab-b224-45a9-9f03-54f912ee4215
                front: "Print Linux kernel log in human-readable format"
                back: "`dmesg --human`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 4e877fe4-c300-43fd-933f-cc1da988684f
                front: "Print Linux kernel log and print incoming messages"
                back: "`dmesg --follow`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 8a1d9119-00a8-4525-b9e7-fcc19d9b1af2
                front: "Flash cards program"
                back: "`anki`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 0544f8eb-46eb-457e-8d69-cf023648db64
                front: "Change screen temperature according to time of day"
                back: "`redshift`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: a25a8bbb-3617-4890-b9dc-318a866ca5a8
                front: "Time tracker"
                back: "`hamster`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 7955cfd7-7d76-4603-b49b-89d59251c6be
                front: "JSON pretty-printer"
                back: "`jshon`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 6d48fdb7-7f4e-4e7f-a6db-e2c0ac0ad469
                front: "Quick and dirty Python HTTP server"
                back: "`python -m SimpleHTTPServer 8080`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 9a499667-bd50-4410-86ca-418f8d1b3cac
                front: "Network monitor by process"
                back: "`nethogs -i enp0s25`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: dc9f6e2d-165f-4be6-a833-1ce12266bce4
                front: "Monitor the progress of data through a pipe"
                back: "`pv`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 1df83c08-703e-4aa3-9d2d-a15ce47bf8e9
                front: "Trace syscalls of running process"
                back: "`strace -p 12345`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 2da5b917-9f07-416b-a7db-4f52ed460b38
                front: "Make ASCII-art banner"
                back: "`banner`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 804e6b8a-5a0d-428a-8f37-78f50de16457
                front: "Convert Windows newlines to Unix"
                back: "`dos2unix`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: edb463b4-0a98-41e4-aafd-db031779509e
                front: "Follow streamed file in new pager"
                back: "`less -F`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: ae49a687-22b7-4b38-8fe9-dcf2340bc87c
                front: "Text formatter to wrap to constant width"
                back: "`fmt`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 66ba52e2-0ff2-4450-948c-885b5dc45662
                front: "Show ASCII table"
                back: "`man ascii`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 46c49bce-49cb-401a-91f7-188cd03cc34a
                front: "Run Matrix effect in console"
                back: "`cmatrix`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 8d6c6663-ab23-4aef-8f40-be4f9efefa6a
                front: "Encode content as QR code"
                back: "`qrencode`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: ebe8171e-21e7-4081-aa99-8a51faa3c624
                front: "Curses Git GUI"
                back: "`tig`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: aa37f76d-9d64-44bb-88ad-50b2031b980c
                front: "GNU parser generator"
                back: "`yacc`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: f12111e2-6520-4689-9d47-825ca6efc6a4
                topic: Pacman
                front: List explicitly installed packages (not as dependencies)
                back: "`pacman -Qe`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 35dbad9a-21ad-4287-86a2-6e516448c36c
                front: "`systemd` - plot startup graph"
                back: "`systemd-analyze plot`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: ec778376-7ac4-4a17-9362-5c6969f866ea
                front: Count occurrences of a string in file
                back: "`grep -c`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 037ae95b-fdf5-4bac-8ba3-a2950ca1732d
                topic: "`grep`"
                front: Search only within files meeting a glob
                back: '`grep --include="*.rb" ...`'
        -
                uuid: 0661c3db-3903-4e75-ac30-82fc31611e50
                front: Screen - attach, including already attached sessions
                back: "`screen -x (session)`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: bb231898-cb17-4f46-8770-24a86c36df2c
                front: Screen - attach to non-attached session
                back: "`screen -r (session)`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: ed27be40-be97-4efd-b713-8a765a8db4fd
                front: Screen - detach
                back: C-a d
        -
                uuid: a479ae33-6970-46a9-8f51-fa11be8f849b
                front: "Creating a symbolic link using `cp`"
                back: "`cp -s (link-target) (link)`"
        -
                uuid: cf65f36d-74c9-456a-8ab2-ec9564a364ea
                front: "`cp -s x y`"
                back: "Creates symbolic link at `y`, pointing to `x`"
        -
                uuid: 9c5adea1-186d-4fa7-87dc-11fa359249d5
                front: Display diff output in two columns
                back: "`diff -y`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: b6977d03-a44d-4e4e-8b5f-7e32d0183d28
                front: mplayer - cycle between alternate audio tracks
                back: '\#'
        -
                uuid: d05a58a8-865d-4399-84e7-a4fa2a75c5cb
                front: Midnight Commander - launch tab completion
                back: '\<Esc\>-\<Tab\>'
        -
                uuid: e37246bb-95bc-43fd-b1ad-00725946b86c
                front: C++ code deduplicator
                back: "`simian`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: a7916680-3788-4922-a38c-38ab4d95ad5c
                front: TUI disk usage visualizer
                back: "`ncdu`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: ef421f30-02d2-411e-8ece-c4e4c53ebe5a
                front: "`patoline`"
                back: Typesetting system
        -
                uuid: f4318a5b-d750-47cc-b934-64fdc0efac88
                topic: Pacman
                front: Mark package as installed as dependency
                back: "`pacman -D --asdeps <pkgs>`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 9f5aacbe-0412-4fd1-960b-471e89e62edb
                front: Count lines of code
                back: "`cloc`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 0e6f1b92-8973-450e-8c08-f704b7bfc8a3
                front: Limit CPU usage of process
                back: "`cpulimit`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 809e0252-68ac-4deb-ac28-2eb212005693
                front: Mount FTP as filesystem
                back: "`curlftpfs`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: a6bbccaa-64fc-4f2a-a4c0-c2d0b3cacf9e
                back: Guitar tuner
                front: "`fmit`"
                include_reverse: true

        -
                uuid: 6575036b-fc4c-471d-98db-a9db63cbaa8e
                front: Limit bandwidth usage
                back: "`wondershaper`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 3740e177-b467-49b4-a17e-f6ce0623b649
                front: Open-source Prolog implementation
                back: "`swipl` (SWI Prolog)"
        -
                uuid: 606afaec-c0a6-4a61-b54c-9956ab7661fb
                front: "`scons`"
                back: Build system
        -
                uuid: 7b383c07-7eaa-457c-a976-5fe3fdaac8e4
                front: Dotfiles management system
                back: "`rcm`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 5747f5c1-c0f9-48ea-97ed-b37033366167
                front: GNU replacement for Matlab
                back: "`octave`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 22018ef4-0a83-4908-b47c-d6d540aa6cb2
                front: JavaScript linter
                back: "`jslint`"
        -
                uuid: 3687d3ec-f046-4974-90f1-8206fae752a9
                front: Color picker
                back: "`gcolor2`"
        -
                uuid: 7675f4e2-9ad8-4c55-adf3-159cf7a2eb66
                front: "`uzbl`"
                back: Web browser
        -
                uuid: 45078b6a-1117-49e1-a78a-1c063766f94d
                front: "`cgdb`"
                back: gdb CLI GUI
        -
                uuid: 84e8770d-cb64-4a75-ad00-45881e4e25eb
                front: "`lftp`"
                back: Command-line FTP client
        -
                uuid: 7e9be7ad-67d4-4be0-a00d-e4bb2ff796fa
                front: "`tmux`"
                back: Console multiplexer, similar to GNU Screen
        -
                uuid: 8a593382-eeb0-4edb-b707-33049de02286
                front: Jekyll
                back: Ruby static page generator
        -
                uuid: 543fdea0-20e1-4429-be6b-5c3907fe3da8
                front: Start SMART tests and read results
                back: "`smartctl -c /dev/sda (-t short|long|conveyance)`"
        -
                uuid: 24e09e05-6d30-4dc2-a6d5-53b66abd8b4e
                front: Silverlight for Firefox & Linux
                back: Pipelight
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: eb31c6c9-3331-4380-ac69-dd05ceda735b
                front: "`gopherjs`"
                back: Go to JavaScript compiler
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: aa74bcfa-3e5e-4952-8636-175de541ef47
                front: Keybase
                back: Identity proof/key sharing site. Keybase.io
        -
                uuid: 4c34d929-09b9-4b82-9904-fd2b949a63cd
                front: OpenShift
                back: Red Hat's web app hosting platform. Includes Go support.
        -
                uuid: 11ba1433-070a-4766-a7b4-a298221c72c2
                front: Wikidata
                back: Wikipedia formalization in RDF form, with statements and quantifiers (sources)
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 27d7031e-6ad3-429b-8912-5f8a6223fa3e
                front: Regex - Zero-width look-ahead assertion
                back: "`(?=regex...)`"
        -
                uuid: 3c5817e0-8c5d-41f5-8f57-8fff308c3a62
                front: Whiteout in PowerPoint
                back: "`w`"
        -
                uuid: f6e28468-b92d-44e1-b082-25f2cc7837d5
                front: Blackout in PowerPoint
                back: "`b`"
        -
                uuid: 7fc48588-1173-454a-a81b-047336aef1d7
                front: Git backup tool
                back: "`git annex`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: aa8deb39-8708-42d8-8404-a23093400360
                front: 'Search all man pages and short descriptions for mentions of "printf"'
                back: "`man -k printf`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: e2060f58-0eaa-439b-8fcd-5c16a351b4d4
                front: 'Look up all man pages named "printf"'
                back: "`man -f printf`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: e8a63dbe-341d-4202-ad51-1e3a76c57bfd
                topic: "man sections"
                front: "1"
                back: "Executable programs or shell commands"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 1132f133-e257-46fa-a1eb-57b8cb2bfb62
                topic: "man sections"
                front: "2"
                back: "System calls (functions provided by the kernel)"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 09d7381e-e7bd-41bf-8c4b-0bcd0a2cab79
                topic: "man sections"
                front: "3"
                back: "Library calls (functions within program libraries)"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 68992887-41d7-48df-9892-9946e5fc6806
                topic: "man sections"
                front: "4"
                back: "Special files (usually found in /dev)"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: ec71edfd-047d-4c65-bc14-50bce3f5e723
                topic: "man sections"
                front: "5"
                back: "File formats and conventions, e.g. /etc/passwd"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: f9de7c2c-c146-4e88-bd54-95f3209c0402
                topic: "man sections"
                front: "6"
                back: "Games"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: e73c0672-eb37-422a-852d-1d4367e757cf
                topic: "man sections"
                front: "7"
                back: "Miscellaneous (including macro packages and conventions), e.g. `man`, `groff`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 31cd0e21-961a-45ec-8068-1fa3e0fe134e
                topic: "man sections"
                front: "8"
                back: "System administration commands (usually only for root)"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 588b3103-a7a8-47be-aa07-3b9f6393b3f4
                topic: "`ssh`"
                front: "Connect to server without pubkey auth"
                back: "`ssh rny.cz -o PubkeyAuthentication=no`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 36b1e5ca-8bd5-47f7-9452-07c7251dd67b
                topic: "`ssh`"
                front: "Enable compression on command-line"
                back: "`ssh -C ...`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: c442269e-24e8-43d7-8d6b-cb73d3898293
                topic: "`ssh`"
                front: "Enable compression in configuration file"
                back: "`Compression yes`"
        -
                uuid: f766e966-7532-4b7b-a41b-7ca60d2edcbd
                topic: "`ssh`"
                front: "`~.` on beginning of line"
                back: "Disconnect forcefully (`~` is `ssh` escape character)"
        -
                uuid: b4885e60-92b9-465f-986f-432010620615
                topic: "`ssh`"
                front: "Disconnect forcefully"
                back: "`~.`, on beginning of line (`~` is `ssh` escape character)"
        -
                uuid: 74fe99ef-4838-4473-a509-140f01cd5a0c
                topic: "`ssh`"
                front: "`~~`"
                back: "Send escape character"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 3ad773ca-d27e-4d0a-a820-5c35e06d6ddf
                topic: "`ssh`"
                front: "Enable X forwarding"
                back: "`ssh -X ...`"
# TODO: whiteout, blackout in Google Docs
        -
                uuid: 4ceab1d5-2924-4bf7-bba9-64d9ee6e0879
                front: Randomly permute input lines
                back: "`shuf`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 518a2d40-73d7-45b8-8c68-2b2330329e17
                front: Show ASCII-art process tree
                back: "`pstree`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: a280e3c8-cb40-4c5f-8ef6-6c5193a7b992
                front: Check, correct and pretty-print HTML files
                back: "`tidy`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 0690643b-c3fa-4d0f-be12-fe11f3d97632
                front: "Tgz up a directory"
                back: "tar cvzf foo.tar.gz cps100"
                # TODO: Which flags do which?
        -
                uuid: 8bd5ef59-fd3b-4297-833a-a51f6c59e194
                topic: Firefox addons
                front: Custom styling by URL
                back: Stylish
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: fd778dd8-35cd-4390-b369-144256137903
                front: Haskell replacement for Xournal
                back: Hoodle
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 21e2cb0f-b573-4ef9-bef6-907133dbbae1
                front: Haskell replacement for Xournal
                back: Hoodle
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 5064f3fb-6d4c-43f4-8d11-4476be548597
                front: Jam
                back: Build tool used by Boost
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 5aca0194-e13f-420d-8af3-03106b509054
                front: pacgraph
                back: Pacman package dependency graph creator
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 0dac8da9-89a2-40d1-8425-0377c71f27a1
                front: Leksah
                back: Haskell IDE
        -
                uuid: c45e42f3-d6d5-4a81-969d-68d7f1a36f98
                front: Pencil
                back: Wireframing tool for Linux
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: bca0cdcb-1b8d-42ca-875f-dbdca5718818
                front: Zathura
                back: Vim-like PDF browser
        -
                uuid: d11079e1-67b4-4a73-a10e-0b9c73d04929
                front: Selenium
                back: Browser automation server
        -
                uuid: ccd11342-2194-469c-98dc-bcad589ba558
                front: Hydrogen
                back: Linux drum machine
        -
                uuid: a01b2370-9568-41c4-ac84-5ba271ecec91
                front: Shamir's secret sharing scheme tool
                back: '`ssss`'
                # TODO: ssss-combine, ssss-split
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: a37e2e7b-dccd-4830-b666-b9c62f110400
                front: '`pocketsphinx`'
                back: TTS
        -
                uuid: 9f7470a4-0aac-400d-8d41-6fbdf4efa867
                front: '`nmtui`'
                back: TUI for NetworkManager
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: cfa2e128-7379-476c-8970-11cbb42ab660
                front: '`fail2ban`'
                back: Banning daemon from logs; supports httpd, vsftpd, sshd, etc.
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 81802f26-c538-4778-b9b8-77090ad668fb
                front: Drop disk cache
                back: '`sync && echo 3 > /proc/sys/vm/drop_caches`'
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 0aaf0db0-7e91-4c39-8871-cb8c717727df
                front: 'Extract sound from video into MP3'
                back: 'ffmpeg -i in.flv -vn -f mp3 out.mp3'
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: f3e496bb-a283-4168-aebc-97915874a483
                topic: "`ffmpeg` flags"
                front: 'Disable recording video'
                back: '`-vn`'
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: a861d48a-b511-46c6-9927-b53ce1e5e717
                topic: "`ffmpeg` flags"
                front: 'Explicitly set format'
                back: '`-f (...)`'
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: a253f826-a37d-4910-9a98-216a9e82c06b
                front: "Convert whitespace-separated input to ASCII table"
                back: "`column -t`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: be62ffbc-42a2-45ef-afec-fc8d9ca20670
                front: "Executable file compressor"
                back: "UPX"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: de501d85-74fc-4196-80db-a1ac0b90c6df
                front: "X-ARF"
                back: "eXtended Abuse Report Format; mail for reporting abuse"
        -
                uuid: e9db0a02-58be-468f-ae6f-887da9103db2
                front: Microsoft's theorem prover
                back: Z3
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 7e2c5888-3867-4239-b1b9-7bca59015622
                topic: Less
                front: "Start following file's tail"
                back: "`F`"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: e53abb54-b816-4477-bb65-de96d0801ed4
                front: "`dialog`"
                back: "Display dialog boxes from shell scripts"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: e15df95f-8b04-4610-a4d8-561d3b26bdf7
                front: "`zenity`"
                back: "Display GTK+ dialog boxes from shell scripts"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 50cfa69c-d22d-453a-9a94-12d312ceba21
                front: "`vanitygen`"
                back: "Bitcoin vanity address generator"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: bffbdd83-494d-4ef0-bc69-d43880a0bec2
                front: "`fc`"
                back: "Open editor, edit last command-line, then run it"
                include_reverse: true
        -
                uuid: 2b5e7cf7-0f15-47b9-82d2-4106ca7f7a5e
                front: "Apache Mahout"
                back: "Distributed or otherwise scalable ML algorithms, mainly collaborative filtering, clustering and classification"
        -
                uuid: ac4c98ff-f261-4673-b377-618b7d94458d
                front: "`gnugo`"
                back: Play Go
        -
                uuid: 8c272a9d-4822-41d2-a0af-55308f12786b
                front: "`cppcheck`"
                back: "Static analysis tool for C/C++ code"
